and because of the rain they turn off the
а из-за дож отключают
electricity yes And why I just don't
свет да А почему я просто не
know for some reason I myself don't understand we have
знаю почему-то сама не пойму у нас
no wind there is no air and everything the transformers can't
ветерок поду нет и всё трансформаторы не
handle what's
выдерживают в чём
the joke
прикол
Hello Hello
Здравствуйте Здравствуйте Вы
Where are you from Dagestan
откуда Из Дагестана
Avar woman Kumyk woman Lac Tabasaran who are you
аварка кумычка лац табасаранец кто вы
Avar woman Avar woman my father  Avar mother
аварка аварка у меня отец аварец мама
Darginka Yes, yes, they went to the
даргинка Да просто да они они поехали в
Soviet Union to Kharkov to study in
Советском Союзе в Харьков учиться в
Ukraine and stayed here got married I was
Украину и остались тут поженились Я
born here in Kharkov But my father Then I
родился Тут в Харькове Но отец Потом мне
was 3 years old my father died so unfortunately I
было 3 года отец умер поэтому я к
don’t know the Avar language Well, my
сожалению аварского языка не знаю Во а
mother is Darginka and she always  said
мама даргинка и она всегда говорила
Dagestan is our Motherland God, how nice it is
Дагестан наша Родина Боже как приятно
to meet people from my
встретить людей со своей
land I have some other relatives
земли У меня ещё родственники какие-то
living in Makhachkala Yes, but I don't communicate with them
есть в Махачкале живут Да но я с ними не
it just turned out that way Yeah,
общаюсь получается как-то так сложилось
Pony And where are you from exactly
Угу Поня А вы откуда именно
Makhachkala maybe you are my cousin
Махачкала може вы моя двоюродная сестра
Yes, how  your name is
Да как вас зовут
Zaira Zaira No she is Gulnara I have
Заира Заира Нет она Гульнара У меня
a sister So Yes
сестра Так что Да
no that would be of course epic so
нет это было бы конечно эпически так по
What do you talk about at chat
О чём общаетесь у чат
roulette I just chat about different topics you are
рулетки просто болтаю на разные темы вам
18 years old
18 лет
I am 20 super what do you work as a
есть мне 20 супер кем работаете э
merchandiser
мерчем мерчендайзером
Yes I
Да
understood how life is in Dagestan I
понял как вообще там жизнь в Дагестане Я
watched the news in the summer they turn off the electricity
смотрел новости летом отключают свет
because they can't handle it Yes
потому что не выдерживают Да
our networks constantly turn off the electricity
сети у нас постоянно выключают свет
because  that the networks can't handle it I just
потому что не выдерживают сети Я просто
can't understand either, I was
тоже не могу понять вот я себе задавался
wondering if Russia is so rich in oil,
вопросом если Россия такая богатая нефть
gas, gold, diamonds, Dagestan is
газ золото алмазы Дагестан богатый на
also rich in resources, oil Why can't they do it in
тоже ресурсы нефть Почему не могут в
Moscow, they can make it so that Muscovites can
Москве могут сделать чтоб москвичи
sit with the lights on, but Dagestan sits and
сидели со светом а Дагестан сидит
turns off the lights in the heat, people, food
отключается в жару свет люди продукты
children are spoiled, they can't live normally,
портятся дети не могут нормально жить у
our
нас
government is stealing
ээ правительство ворует
electricity. What kind of government are we?
электричество Какое правительство нас
Recently, some
недавно недавно посадили какого-то
official was jailed for
чиновника за то что он
stealing electricity
украл свет
for almost 3 billion rubles, and the question is how did he steal
на почти 3 млрд руб а вопрос как украл
electricity? For example, you
свет например
can steal potatoes, but how did he
украсть картошку можно а как вот он
steal electricity for 3?  billion rubles where did he
украл свет на 3 млрд рублей куда он его
put it I don't know him Well it turns out he
дел Я не знаю он Ну получается должен
should have spent this money from the state
деньги от государства должен был
on
потратить их на
electricity I don't know what  in a way, but
электричество не знаю Каким образом но
he took them for himself
он забрал их себе
and saved on us, turned off the electricity
а на нас экономил отключал Нам свет
to save money, not just I know that the
чтобы сэкономить не просто я знаю что
electricity was turned off there not because they were
там отключался свет не потому что
saving money, but because there is not
экономить а потому что этих мощностей не
enough power and the transformers can't
хватает и э трансформаторы не
handle it either Well, nothing has changed there for 20 years under such a load
выдерживают также Ну такой нагрузки за
Because the money that
менялось Потому что деньги которые
should have been spent on new
должны были потратить на новые
transformers was put into their own pockets, I
трансформаторы поставили себе в карманы
understand, that's more understandable, yes. And what do
понял вот это уже более понятно да А как
you think, uh, who is to blame for the fact that
вы считаете ээ кто виноват в том что
Russia is so rich and people live so
Россия такая богатая а люди живут так
poorly? I don't
бедно не
know. Well, for example, who could it be America's
знаю Ну например кто может быть Америка
fault, Germany's fault, who  it is to blame that
виновата Германия кто виноват в том что
people in Russia live poorly because
люди в России живут бедно из-за того что
they have so much gold and
имеют столько золота
diamonds people probably themselves are half to blame
алмазов люди наверное Сами виноваты
I don't
наполовину Я не
know And today they turned off the power in Makhachkala
знаю А сегодня отключали в Махачкале
because I thought that today there
потому что я вроде считал что сегодня
were also some power outages in Makhachkala
Света были
I don't know  I was at work all day
Я не знаю я была целый день на работе У
We had a
нас
generator working today generator Yes
генератор сегодня работал генератор Да у
you have Uh-huh and that is to say that the power was turned off
Вас Угу а то есть получается отключили
and you turned on the generator You had
свет и вы включили генератор У вас был
power
свет
yes yes I understand I seemed to say yes that it's been 6
да да понял Я вроде говорил да что 6
hours already there is no car or Light today is
часов уже нету махачка или Света сегодня
also interesting And how  so it turns out that
тоже интересно А как так получается что
Russia is fighting with Ukraine in
Россия воюет с Украиной в
Ukraine how does it happen that Russia is fighting with
Украине как получается что Россия воют с
Ukraine in Ukraine the light can be heard
Украиной в Украине свет слышно
now yes yes how does it happen that
сейчас да да как так получается что
Russia is fighting with Ukraine in Ukraine there is
Россия воюет с Украиной в Украине есть
light And you in Makhachkala have no
свет А у вас в Махачкале нету
light I don’t know here it just started
света Я не знаю у нас просто Дождь
raining and from  - because of the rain they turn off the
пошёл так а из-за дождя отключают
electricity yes and why I just don't
свет да а почему я просто не
know why I don't understand myself we have
знаю почему так сама не понима у нас
no wind and the transformers can't
ветерок поду нет и всё трансформаторы не
handle everything what's
выдерживают в чём
the joke and haven't they tried to somehow
прикол а не пробовали там как-то к
contact Putin so that he would solve this
Путину обратиться чтобы он решил этот
issue I don't know
вопрос я не знаю
but what  people are talking among themselves about how to
а что говорят люди вот между собой как
solve this issue with
решить этот вопрос со
light here, in my opinion, everyone has already
светом тут по-моему уже все к этому
gotten used to it, that is, they have already come to terms with the fact
привыкли то есть уже смирились с тем Да
that there is no light
что света нету
Yeah, I understand Well, as if they didn’t think
Угу понял Ну а как бы не задумывались
that it is possible to live
что можно жить
better, I don’t
лучше не
know. How do you think why in  Europe
знаю вот Как вы считаете почему в Европе
for example in Estonia is small Yes, no one
например в Эстонии маленькой Да никто не
turns off the electricity Everyone lives with
отключает свет Все живут со
electricity the
светом
government does not steal
правительство не ворует
electricity I understand And what do you think is it
свет понял А как ты считаешь это
only your Dagestani
виновато только ваше дагестанское
government or the
правительство или вообще
Russian government in general to blame Well, it turns out that it is
Российская Ну получается что
Dagestani because the Russian
дагестанская потому что российское
government allocated money and
правительство выделило деньги а
Dagestan put them in her pocket
дагестанское в карман поставила их
that is the Russian government is not
то есть российское правительство не
to blame for the regions living poorly
виновато в том что регионы живут бедно
Yes I don't
Да я не
know Well yes And how much is your salary
знаю Ну да А сколько вот у вас зарплаты
there in
там в
Dagestan Well for me well it's different
Дагестане Ну у меня ну по-разному
well for
ну
example Well
пример Ну в
2,000 a day I earn 20 dollars in
день 2.000 Я зарабатываю 20 долларов в
day that is for 20 working days you
день то есть за 20 рабочих дней вы
will earn 40,000 rubles 400 dollars for 2
заработаете 40.000 руб 400 долларов за 2
weeks for 20 working days Well in a month
недели за 20 рабочих дней Ну в месяце
if you work 5 days, work two days,
если работать 5 дней работать два
rest, it turns out 2122 working days I
отдыхать получается 2122 рабочих дня я
think so I can go to
считаю я могу выйти на
work any day when I
работу любой день когда мне
want and I  they just pay for it
захочется и мне за это просто
I understand And what professions
платят понял А какие профессии самое
earn the most in
больше зарабатывают в
Dagestan I don't
Дагестане не знаю
even know well recently For some reason
даже ну последнее время Прям почему-то
everyone has been drawn to
все потянулись на
photo shoots
фотосъёмки
see and
см а
why I don't
почему я не
know we have a lot of which
знаю у нас прямо очень много которые
there are even bloggers who just take
есть даже блогеры которые просто делают
photos they are all popular and  This is how
фотографии всё они популярны и на этом
they make money Well, bloggers also
зарабатывают деньги Ну блогеры тоже у
make money But for example, I also saw
зарабатываю А вот например я ещё видел
that in Dagestan you had problems there,
что в Дагестане у вас там были проблемы
that a gas station
что заправка взорвалась
exploded  it was burning in Makhachkala, I think, also like
было горело это в Махачкале вроде тоже
that, yeah And why did it explode like that? It turns out that
так да А из-за чего она так
something was stored there, fertilizer, yeah, it
хранились что-то там хра удобрение да да
just somehow passed and eventually exploded,
как-то перешло уже и в итоге взорвалось
some other cylinders exploded there, I understand, I understand.
там ещ кае баллоны взорвало понял Понял
Listen, do you have anyone?  -someone from my acquaintances
Слушай а у тебя есть кто-то из знакомых
who is fighting in
кто воюет в
Ukraine or fought Well,
Украине или воевал
my uncle died there And what happened to him
ну у меня дядя там умер А что с ним
there was some moment
случилось там что-то был какой-то момент
that
что
some I don’t know what it’s
какая-то Я не знаю как это
called but there was an explosion, they
называется ну взрыв произошёл
blew it up And how is your uncle  he got to war
взорвали А как твой дядя попал на войну
he went himself or his mobile Zro he
он сам пошёл или его мобили Зро он сам
went himself for money
пошёл за деньги
yes for family Yes not for himself work this is
да для семь Да не для себ рабо это
he didn't work for anyone it turns out he
он никем не работал он получается
spent half his life even most of it in prison he wasn't accepted anywhere
просидел в тюрьме его никуда не
and in the end he was taken to war And  he is like that
и в итоге его взяли на войну И он такой
at least I will do something for my children
хотя бы так своим детям что-нибудь
he was taken from prison to war or
сделаю его из тюрьмы взяли на войну или
he is from
он со
Freedom from Freedom
Свободы со Свободы
more than 5 years have passed I understood and he is in
уже больше 5 лет прошло понял а он в
prison What was he in prison for
тюрьме За что сидел
Before  I don't know, they
Раньше я не знаю
didn't even say it Okay, he went
даже не говорили это Окей он пошёл типа
to war to earn at least something for his family
на войну чтобы для своей семьи хоть
Yes And how long did he spend
что-то заработать Да А сколько он прово
there Eva, not long,
там недолго
how many months probably That is, he didn't even really
сколько месяцев наверно То есть он даже
earn anything, I don't know how much they said 2
заработал не знаю сколько там говорили 2
million  to my Well in Russia it goes
млн по-моему Ну в России идёт
as compensation
как компенсация
for a dead dad For a dead dad
за за мёртвого папу За мёртвого папу
or for a dead husband 7 million there is I heard
либо за мёртвого мужа 7 млн есть слышал
yes Well yes that goes as compensation
да Ну да вот идёт как компенсация
I understood it turns out in dollars it comes out to
понял это получается в долларах выходит
somewhere around 70,000 dollars yes But I
где-то 70.000 долларов да А вот
wonder what you can buy for these  7
интересно что можно купить за вот эти 7
million you have in
млн у вас в
Dagestan
Дагестане
m you can have a good house plus a car
м можно хороший дом плюс ещё машину
I understand And what bought this money
понял А что купило это эти Деньги
who got it his children or his wife
получила его кто его дети или его жена
got it who
получила кто
got it his wife understood And what did his
получил его жена понял А что купила его
wife buy with these 7 million
жена на эти 7 млн
I don't
я вообще не
know at all well somehow  there house car didn't
знаю ну как бы там дом машину не
communicate didn't see her anymore after the
общались не видела её больше после
funeral no one saw her anymore and before the
похорон её никто не видел больше а до
funeral you saw her often
похорон вы её часто Видели
Yes
Да
No so she lives with you in Makhachkala Yes she
Нет так она живёт с вами в Махачкале Да
lived No she lives in Kizlyar  Kizlyar I know
жила Нет она живёт в Кизляре Кизляр знаю
there are Kizlyar knives yes
там кизлярские ножи да
that is she came to the funeral
то есть она на похороны приехала сем
took seven million and in short she
лямов забрала и Короче
left and the children where they
поехала а дети Где
live Well here it turns out they were not his
живут Ну десь вообще получается не его
relatives
родные были
[music]
[музыка]
at Well it turns out they stayed with his wife
у Ну они получается с женой его
now I
сейчас дальше остались
understood And for what if these are children  not his
понял А для какой если это дети не его
type why did he go to kill people in
типа для какой он пошёл убивать людей в
Ukraine for
Украине для
them Cool And what do you think, did he
них Прикольно А как ты считаешь он
do the right thing by going to such a
правильно сделал что пошёл в такой
way to earn money for his
способ заработать для своей
family Probably not And what about his children What do they
семьи Наверное нет А а дети его Что
say and his
говорят и
wife I
жена вообще
don't know at all Well, I haven't seen his children  his
не знаю Ну детей его я не видела на его
funeral And well, this is for example
похоронах А хорошо вот это например Это
He is your mother's brother or your father's brother if
он брат твоей мамы или твоего папы если
he is your uncle who is he my
он твой дядя кого он во брат моей
grandmother's brother Yes, my grandmother's brother And what do your
бабушки Да брат бабушки А что твои
relatives say about him going
родственники говорят про то что он пошёл
to
на
war
войну
Well, when the floor
ну он вообще когда пол
turns out, he told about it in  the day when he was
получается сказа об этом в день когда он
already heading there so that no
уже отправлялся туда чтобы типа его
one would stop him and everyone was arguing about
никто не останавливал и все ругались там
something there Why did he
что-то Зачем так
do that then when he died they also
сделал потом уже когда умер тоже
said that he
говорили что что-то на смерть что ли
was going
пошёл
there to his death or something yes And is there anyone else I know
туда да А кто-то ещё из знакомых есть
who died or something
кто погиб или
wounded
раненный
well no one from the family but it often happened
ну из семьи нету но бывало часто
that there was a situation where someone died at my mother's work
ситуация что там у мамы на работе у
Here are my friends' fathers uncles
умер Вот у подруг отцы дяди
also huge By the way I also see from
тоже огромный Я кстати тоже смотрю из
Dagestan such a huge number of
Дагестана такое огромное количество
dead Why don't Muscovites go to war
погибших Почему москвичи не идут воевать
Why did they bring Dagestan to  poverty
Почему они Дагестан довели до бедности
Yes and for Dagestanis to go and die for money
Да и чтобы дагестанцы шли за деньги
in Ukraine for these Muscovites it
умирать в Украине за этих москвичей так
turns out that way
получается
Yeah and why does Moscow take all the
Угу а почему Москва забирает себе все
money, resources, oil Yes and only returns
деньги ресурсы нефть Да а возвращает
coffins to Dagestan I don't
гробы не
know Yes And who do you think is to blame for
знаю да А как ты считаешь кто виноват в
this war between Russia and Ukraine
том что идёт эта война России и Украины
I don't know at all I don't understand anything about this
я вообще не знаю я не понимаю в этом
Well, it's just that we are like ordinary
ничего Ну просто вот да мы как простые
people I am an ordinary person and you are an ordinary person so to
люди я простой человек и ты простой вот
understand what you think Yes,
чтобы разобраться как ты думаешь Да
because of what this
из-за чего началась эта
war started because of the government probably
война из-за правительства наверно
some Well, my Dad came  I
какого Ну всей у меня Папа пришёл мне
have to
пора
go and what dad doesn't allow to
идти а что папа не разрешает
talk dad doesn't allow to
разговаривать папа не разрешает
talk
разговаривать
Why I don't know doesn't like such things
Почему не знаю не любит такие вещи
n Why You're a grown woman can
н Почему Ты же взрослая женщина можешь
talk Well I don't know just doesn't
говорить Ну я не знаю просто не
allow he doesn't talk to anyone at all
разрешает он вообще ни с кем не
no
разговаривать не
correspondence he is some kind of
переписываться он у тебя какой-то
religious
религиозный
so it's
сильно так
time to say
пора до
goodbye write to y Telegram right now
свидания пись на й Telegram прямо зараз
axis VN
ось ВН
apok this is very and very important YouTube is busy
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
with us through scarg Orcs in your ban and very
нас через скарг Орки в твый бан и дуже
many videos I don't show people sometimes I don't
багато вдео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about streams to that  in order for
показуе информация про стримы тому для
us to Mali active links
того щоб ми Мали активный звязок
are written right now and Popik there in
пишиться прямо зараз а Попик там в
telegrams will okrim video also interesting and
телеграми окрим видео ще теж цикава и
useful information and we will oblige you
корисна информация и мы повинни з вами
to keep constant operational links
тримати постийний оперативный звязок
independently in that will show you about this
незалежно в того чи покаже вам про це
YouTube Glory to Ukraine
YouTube Слава украини
write and
пиши а